It might be related to the medication
可能跟吃的药有关系
Recently, it's the toughest allergy season of the year
最近进入了一年最难过的这个过敏期啊
So on Qixi, I was planning to update
所以七夕当天本来说要更新
But it didn't happen
结果就没更新
Plus, I've been taking care of the kids these past couple of days
加上这两天带孩子
So that's why I'm updating today
所以拖到今天才更新
That's not important though
这个不重要啊
My second book
我的第二本书啊
Is currently in the writing process
正在这个撰写当中
Actually, I submitted the manuscript a while ago
其实我的书稿早就交了
But to be honest, I wasn't really satisfied with most of the content
但是其实书稿大部分的内容呢呃我是不太满意
So I rewrote it again
所以后来又重新写了一版啊
Now it's essentially the third version
现在是等于是第三版啊
For the third edition,
第三版来讲的话
most of the content is actually different from before.
就是跟以前的内容其实有大部分不一样
As you all know, my first book was quite conservative,
大家知道我第一本书出的呢比较保守
due to the need for approval at that time,
那时候出于过审的目的啊
I wrote in a rather conservative manner,
写的比较保守啊
and included a lot of content,
写了很多啊
it was, how should I put it,
非常怎么说呢
very watertight,
滴水不漏的话啊
which isn't really my natural way of speaking or writing.
不是我的真实的这种说话的行文的风格啊
I will let loose completely in my second book.
我第二本书会完完全全的放飞自我
So it has great value as a favorite.
所以非常有收藏价值
Uh, I mentioned in the last preview. I originally said this episode would be about the Qixi Festival. But actually, this episode will still talk about love.
呃我呃上一期预告了一下 本来说这一期要说这个这个这个这个七夕的事啊 但是其实呃这一期还是讲这个爱情的这个事情
When discussing love,
讲这个爱情这事情呢
I want to start by sharing a viewpoint with everyone.
首先就跟大家说明一个观点
My perspective is,
我的观点呢是
No matter what the outcome of your life turns out to be.
无论你最后这一生的结局是什么
The lifestyle you choose
你选择了什么样的生活方式
How would you explain it?
都要怎么说呢
Be at peace with yourself
问心无愧
Don’t make it out to be a big deal
不要觉得是一件很大的事啊
The original purpose of creating these holidays
就是说本身这些节日的创造的目的呢
Whether it’s based on mythology
无论是出于神话也好
Or historical anecdotes
还是出于典故也好
Take Saint Valentine, for instance
甭管是这个圣瓦伦丁啊
Who stood up for young people in Rome
这个为了这个罗马的这个青少年啊
To save this young couple, they sacrificed themselves
为了这个青年男女牺牲了自己
Or is it the story of the Cowherd and the Weaver Girl crossing the magpie bridge
还是说咱们这个牛郎织女的鹊桥的故事啊
No matter what
无论怎么样啊
The East has its own Valentine's Day
东方有东方的情人节
The West has its own Valentine's Day
西方有西方的情人节
Some people say
也有人说啊
Valentine's Day should be spent with one's lover
情人节就应该跟情人过
Why should it be spent with one's wife
为什么要跟老婆过了啊
We shouldn't promote such unhealthy values
这种不良的这个价值观呢咱们不能提倡呃
Sure, let's talk about it. First, let's discuss why this thing exists. Why do people fall in love? It's a form of genetic selection.
当然来讲的话 我们就说一下这个首先这个东西它为什么存在啊 啊人为什么会有爱情啊 它是一种基因上面的一种选择
Because genes need to constantly evolve.
因为基因本身需要把自己不断的进化
And be passed down.
不断的遗传下去啊
It's actually the selfish gene.
其实是自私的基因
If you've read the book, you'll know.
这本书大家如果看的话
Humans are merely vehicles for genes.
人只不过是基因
It's a tool for replicating oneself.
就是用来复制自己的工具啊
That's one perspective.
这是一种观点呃
As you all know, I tend to advocate for, how should I put it,
大家也知道我是比较提倡的这种怎么说呢
utilitarian or realistic thinking.
功利思想或者说是现实主义的思想啊
Machiavelli primarily discussed these ideas.
马基亚维利讲的主要是这些
But in terms of my personal conduct,
但是其实我本人做人来讲的话
I have already transcended the utilitarian phase.
我已经是超越功力阶段的这么一种状态啊
Indeed, love does have its pragmatic side.
就是说爱情本身的确有他功利的一面啊
It involves what you might call a strong alliance, right?
有他这个所谓的强强联合呀对吧
It's about being well-matched.
门当户对呀
There is this aspect.
有这一面
But love itself, no matter how old you are,
但是爱情本身呢啊无论你是什么岁数的人啊
you shouldn't turn your back on it.
都不应该把你的后背对着爱情啊
That is, it's something grand and sacred.
也就是说这个东西本身他是很高大很神圣的啊
This is the core idea of this episode. How should we approach the choices in love? Because when we are young, Take me, for example. When I was six or seven I already had someone I liked back then
这就是我这一期的核心的这个理念 到底啊应该怎么样面对爱情的这个选择 因为在我们年轻的时候啊 比如说你像我啊 六七岁的时候 其实那时候我就已经啊已经有喜欢的人了
Right?
对不对
There was that innocent feeling of youth
有那种懵懂的青春的感觉
Actually, from elementary school to junior and senior high school
其实我最开始啊甭管是上初中还是上高中还是小学
The people I liked
喜欢的这几个人
I still have a soft spot for them
我到现在啊也仍然是比较喜欢
I still admire them
比较欣赏啊
But it doesn't mean that everyone you like should end up together
但是不是说所有的你喜欢的人就都要在一起
And often when we talk about it
而很多的时候来讲
we mention the process of courtship
我们说到这个求偶的这个过程
which involves the exchange of interests among adults
它又牵扯到成年人之间的利益交换
and it also involves issues of sexuality
又又牵扯到性的问题
So, I often see sex and love as two separate things
所以很多的时候我是把性跟这个爱情是把他看成是两件事情啊
Someone who is sexually attractive
性这方面有吸引力的人
may not necessarily evoke strong feelings between you two
未必你们俩真正有非常强烈的感情
This is an inequality in the adult world
这就是成人世界中的一个不等式
Many people tend to consider affection and love together
就是说很多人他是把这个情与爱放在一块考虑的
Some people can separate things and consider them individually.
有的人呢就是能把他的分离来考虑
I belong to the category of those who can separate things.
我是属于分离的那一系列的
But at its core, it's impossible for these things to be completely separated. If you don't have any good feelings towards a person, you really don't. This is what I think is the biggest difference between men and women. Men can completely detach emotionally,
但是核心来说就是说这个东西它也不可能完全分离 如果你对这个人一点好感都没有 你其实是啊 这也是我觉得男女之间的最大区别 男生是可以来讲完全脱离情感啊
and pursue someone solely for sexual reasons,
而是只为了性去追求谁
or care about someone in that way.
或者去在意谁啊
I think girls, in this aspect,
女生我觉得在这一方面
apart from a very few exceptions,
除了极个别的人以外啊
most people still have some liking for this,
大部分人还是多多少少会喜欢这个
how should I put it,
怎么说呢
this partner, this significant other,
这个伴侣这个对象的啊
it's impossible to have absolutely no interest at all,
不可能完完全全一点好感都没有
otherwise, they wouldn't be able to go through with it,
那他是下不去嘴的啊
but I personally think, no matter how much we discuss this,
呃但是我本身觉得这个东西无论再怎么讨论呢
let's face it, this is a form of consumerist behavior.
咱们说啊这是一种消费主义的行为啊
To lure a man
诱引男的啊
No matter who it is
不管是谁啊
You should spend some money
你去花几个钱啊
To satisfy the opposite sex
去这个满足异性啊
This is also a form of societal guidance
这也是社会对你的一种规劝
This is indeed the case
这个东西的确是这样
He has this characteristic
他有这个属性
Right?
对不对
Because your country and society are not developing
因为你这个国家社会不发展啊
No one is reproducing to increase the population.
没有人去繁殖新的人口啊
The community would die out, wouldn't it?
这个族群不就灭了嘛
Right?
对不对
But from the perspective of personal aspirations,
但是从我们个人的追求的角度来讲
I've always been a staunch advocate of single life.
我一直是秉耿直秉持的一个单身主义啊
This idea of being single and independent. It wasn't something I had from the beginning, nor did it come from not being able to find a partner. It came from a place of personal choice. Or, the attitude one has towards life or towards personal cultivation.
独身主义的这么一种思想啊 并不是一开始就有这种思想 也并不是因为找不到伴侣了才有这种思想 而是从一个人啊 或者说从一个人的个人生的态度或者说修行的态度啊
I believe that a person can maintain a single status.
我是认为一个人保持一种单身的状态
Sometimes you might travel with others,
你有的时候有可能跟别人同行啊
for a period or work together with someone,
一段时间或者跟别人共事
or be with someone,
或者跟谁在一起
but these situations are not permanent states.
但是这种东西它不是一种永恒的状态
I am against marriage.
我是反对婚姻的啊
I have no interest in marriage at all.
我是对婚姻一点的兴趣
You could say, none whatsoever.
可以说都没有啊
Actually, my marriage was also a result of a momentary impulse.
其实我当初结婚也是属于一时冲动啊
Actually, I've always been a person who doesn't believe in marriage.
也其实我一直是一个啊不婚主义者啊
Because I think love should be a part of life,
因为我认为啊爱情是应该有的
but having a family doesn't necessarily mean you need to get married.
但是婚姻啊不一定有家庭是应该有的
Marriage isn't always a must.
但是婚姻不一定非得有啊
That's how I see it.
我是这么看的
And that's how I've consistently lived my life.
我也是这么呃不停的实践过来的
But I still believe that one of the most precious things in this world might be the kind of relationship young people have,
但是我仍然要说就是人世间最可贵的可能就是青年人的那种啊
the childhood sweethearts.
青梅竹马呀
Those impulsive couples on campus
校园的那种冲动情侣啊
are really great Although I always say that couples shouldn't flaunt their affection Flaunting affection leads to a quick breakup Don't make us single people feel left out But to be honest When I see those couples in my social circle
非常好啊 虽然我一直说啊那个情侣不要晒秀恩爱 秀恩爱死得快 不要那个让我们单身狗吃狗粮 但是本身来讲 我看到我朋友圈里那些情侣啊
whether they are followers
不管是粉丝
or colleagues and classmates
还有什么同事同学之类的
I tend to bless people from the heart
我还是精神上就是倾向于祝福人家的
there's no need to curse them
没有必要你去诅咒人家嘛
right?
对不对
it's quite normal
很正常
there's genuine affection in the world
人间自有真情在啊
when someone chooses to be with the one they love
一个人愿意跟这个爱的人在一起
and both are committed to each other
而且两个人能够双向奔赴啊
to build a family together
能够组建一个家庭
that's a truly beautiful thing
这是一件很美好的事情啊
But if you don’t have the chance to start a family
但是如果你没有这个机会组建家庭
or haven’t found your soulmate
没有找到自己的意中人啊
and remain single or involuntarily single
保持了一种单身或者是非自愿单身的
don’t feel too down about it
也不要觉得自己呢很难过
because in this world
因为人世之间啊
with the vastness of the universe
天地之广阔
there are many pursuits to follow
有很多事情可以追求
and so much to explore
有很多东西可以去探索啊
as you can see, I’m not in a state of freedom myself
你看我现在就不是一个自由的状态啊
It's because I have kids
就是因为有孩子
so I have to spend time with them every week
所以每周都得陪孩子
and because I have parents
因为有父母
you know, parents shouldn't travel far when they're around
父母在不远游嘛
right?
对不对
and they're not in the best health
父母身体又不好
so you can't go too far away I can only stay at a place for up to two weeks if I want to go abroad It's no more than a month. So, we need to hurry back as soon as possible. Why? Because this is the time when your parents need you the most in their entire lives.
你就不可能去一个地方太远 我最多到一个地方两个礼拜啊 我超要去国外的话 最多也就一个月啊 所以就得赶往赶赶紧往回赶 为什么 因为父母啊这个时间其实是他这一辈子最需要你的时候
For children, before the age of 12,
孩子啊在12岁之前
or even before 16,
或者说在16岁之前
it's a crucial period for building a father-son relationship.
也是这辈子这个父子感情建立的一个关键时候
This is when they need you the most.
他这个时候是最需要的人
After 16 to 18 years old,
16~18岁以后啊
Or when the parents are really old
或者说父母特别老了
You have to find someone to take care of them
不得不找人看护了
Once they're in a nursing home
进了养老院以后
It doesn't really concern you anymore
那就跟你来讲就没有什么关系了
Right?
对不对
In that case
那个东西来讲的话
The time you can help out will be less
那就是你能够帮上忙的时间就少了啊
I'm not saying
我不是说啊
You shouldn't take care of your parents at that time
就那个时候你就不应该照顾父母了
That's when healthcare and caregiving professionals become even more important.
就是那个时候医护人员跟看护人员对他们的作用来讲就更大了
Nowadays, parents are in their sixties or early seventies.
现在父母在六七十岁这个年代啊
They haven’t reached their late seventies or eighties yet.
还没到八九十六七十岁
This is the time when you should be there for your parents.
这个年代正是应该陪伴父母的时候
Although their health may not be great,
父母的身体还啊虽然不好
it’s still okay to spend time with them, chat, and talk.
但是还OK你陪陪他们说说话呀
Take them on trips,
陪他们旅旅游啊
and share these moments together.
陪他们共享这个时光啊
I think that’s wonderful.
我觉得很好
But if you get married, you won't be able to do that. You will get married, no matter what, you will start a new family. There are people who live with their parents, but he will definitely live with one set of parents, and certainly not with both sets of parents. So, in many cases, I've heard about people opting for 'marriage pooling' now.
但是如果你结婚 你就做不到啊 你要结婚 不管是怎么样 你会成立新的家庭 跟父母生活的人也有 但是他肯定是跟一方父母生活 也肯定不能跟两方父母生活 所以很多的时候那个啊我现在就听说有拼婚
There's the practice of walking marriage
有走婚
where you return to your own family on weekends
就是周末回自己家
and live in your small family during the week
平时在自己的小家啊
I think this is quite good
我觉得这样挺好
But for those of us who are divorced and have children
但是像我们这种离婚有孩子
I can spend time with my parents on a regular basis
然后呢我能平时跟父母在一起呢
I feel very happy
我感觉也很快乐
I've had several times in the past
我曾经有好几次啊
and even now, I still think about moving out
包括现在都是想啊搬出去啊
I have a small place of my own
自己用一个小家
I set up another broadband connection myself
我自己再拉一条宽带
I got another computer for myself
自己再弄一台电脑
Isn't it great to do whatever I want in my own space?
自己那块儿想干什么干什么不好吗
But I always feel that
但是我总是觉得啊
with my parents still around
父母还在以后
I will be living alone for a long time
我独身生活的时间会很长啊
the kids grow up
孩子长大了啊
she leaves me
她离开我了
Or he lives with his mother.
或者说他跟他妈在一块生活啊
Isn't it that everyone has their own life?
是不是人他有自己的人生啊
His parents passed away back then.
父母那个时候撒手人寰了
He's no longer around.
人也不在了
I have decades of solitude to enjoy in the future.
我以后有的是几十年的那个独身的时间可以享用
So I don't need to rush at this moment.
所以我是不用太着急这一时的啊
When I was young, I thought I went through a lot for love. Or rather, for emotions, I took many detours. But looking back now, those so-called detours were actually smooth paths. It's all worth it.
呃年轻的时候我觉得为了爱情 或者说为了感情走过很多弯路 但是这些弯路呢所谓的弯路呢其实到现在看都是坦途 都是值得的啊
Whether you achieve or don't achieve your ideal goal,
无论你追求的到还是追求不到你的这个理想的对象啊
you shouldn't be sad.
其实你都不应该难过
Why shouldn't you be sad?
为什么不应该难过呢
Because the person you like changes over time.
因为你喜欢的人他是随着时间他会变的
And the person you like,
而且你喜欢的人
is not just the person themselves,
他这个东西他并不是这个人本身
but what they represent—a set of values and an impression you project onto them.
而是它所代表的一种价值观和一种你的一种印象的投射
In fact, you are gradually perfecting the image of the other person.
其实你是把对方逐渐完美化的
Including love
包括爱情
Any kind of love
任何爱情
Or with your wife
或者你在你的妻子
During your honeymoon phase
在你的新婚期间的话
You might think she's perfect
你也会认为她什么都好啊
Your husband seems perfect too
丈夫也是什么都好
The same goes for new relationships
男女朋友也是新交的时候
The feeling is really great
那感觉是非常不错的
But as time goes on
但是时间越长啊
When it comes to human beings,
人这种动物来讲
they tend to gradually grow tired of someone,
它就是会逐渐厌倦一个人啊
get used to someone,
习惯一个人
over time,
慢慢来讲
you start to feel a sense of aversion towards them,
你们就对他开始产生厌恶的感觉了
and begin to develop a sense of novelty with a new person,
又开始对新的对象呢产生一种新鲜感
people are always inclined to seek new things and get tired of old ones, there's nothing wrong with that, that's just how they're wired. Why did he encode it this way? Because it's the same old story. Genes need to have their own process of transmission. If you want to understand how reproduction, love, and sexuality work,
这个人永远是喜新厌旧的啊 没有什么错啊 他就是这么编码的 他为什么要这么编码呢 因为这个还是那句话 基因他需要有自己的一个传递的过程啊 如果你想明白这个生殖爱情性这些东西是怎么回事
this isn't just a matter of sociology.
这个是不光是社会学的范畴啊
There's sociology,
因为有社会学
there's the sociology of sexuality,
有性社会学
and there's also the field of anthropology.
还有人类学的范畴啊
Right?
对不对
How does a person survive?
人他怎么生存
How do various species reproduce?
怎么繁衍各种不同的物种
How do they mate?
它怎么样的交配啊
How do new species emerge?
怎么样产生新的物种
There's a complex mechanism behind this.
这个东西它是有很复杂的一个机理在里边了
And it involves biology,
而且还有涉及到那个生物啊
as well as medicine,
涉及到医学
the hormones in your brain,
你脑内的这些这些激素啊
how are they distributed?
这怎么分配呢
How are neurons distributed?
神经元是怎么分配的
What substances are secreted?
分泌的什么东西
How do dopamine and endorphins produce these substances?
多巴胺内啡肽它怎么样产生这种东西
What's the deal with hormones?
荷尔蒙是怎么回事
So these things are influenced by multiple factors.
所以这些东西他是受多元的东西影响的
It's not just one or two simple factors.
不是一个一个两个简单的因素
But for me,
但是对于我来讲的话
all of this is a kind of illusion.
这一切呢就是这一切本身是一种幻想啊
It's a delusion.
是一种虚妄啊
It's not something tangible. But look at all the people I used to like. But when you bring it back to reality, they are just ordinary people. If you think about it carefully,
不是那种实际实际的东西 而你看我当初喜欢过的这些所有的人呢 但是你还原到现实当中 他们都是一个个普通的人 如果你仔细想想
spending your life with them,
与他们长相厮守
living together every day,
天天生活在一块啊
sharing meals and burps,
吃饭打嗝
and all the other daily routines.
放屁拉屎
These things might not look as aesthetically pleasing when placed together.
这些东西坐在一块可能就没有那么没有美感了
A lot of things seem most appealing when they're just out of reach.
可能很多东西都是在你追求不到的时候
They feel the most special then.
他最有感觉
But once you get what you want,
等你追求到了
whether it's taking the car out or bringing it home,
把这车啊提款了或拿回家了
you might get tired of it after a few days.
开几天你可能腻了啊
Why do people sell used cars?
为什么会有人卖二手车呢
It's often because they get tired of them after driving for a while.
就是这样开的时间长了就腻歪了啊
So, many times, that's just how it goes.
所以很多的时候就是这样
So the state you once desperately wanted to achieve
所以你当初使劲想去追求的一种状态啊
might just be a phase in your life
他可能只是你人生中的某一个阶段
and whether or not you enter this phase
而你进入不进入这种阶段
doesn't really have a significant impact on your future
对你今后的人生其实没有太大的影响
so I'm saying don't get too fixated on love
所以我就是说大家不要因为爱情而执着于此啊
fixating on a particular person or a certain idea
执着于某一个人或者某一种观念
or thinking you must be with someone
或者说我必须要跟谁在一起
or you must not be single
或者我必须要不能单身啊
you need to find a partner
我要找到一个伴侣啊
I think, as someone on a spiritual journey, the first thing is not to have any such constraints, my behavior in a certain place, if I were to find a girlfriend,
我倒觉得作为我来讲一个修行当中的人呢 这个首先就是不能有任何的这种束缚 我在某一个地方的这种行为啊 如果我找了一个那个女孩子的话啊
for instance, get married or something,
比如说结婚了或者怎么样
she would inevitably restrict me,
她就必然会束缚我啊
her family,
他的家庭啊
the place she’s from,
他所在的地方
her career
他的职业
His life plan
他的人生规划啊
is definitely, for me
肯定就是对于我来讲的话
he needs to make some choices
他要有所取舍
for him
对于他来讲的话
I also need to make some choices
我也要有所取舍
it's like being a couple
就是你就像夫妻一样
you always have to give up part of your lifestyle and your dreams
总是要放弃一部分自己的生活方式跟自己的梦想啊
to build this family
为了建设这个家庭啊
being together
所谓的在一块儿
But in reality,
但是实际上来讲
when you actually take the road less traveled,
当你真正走上了那个未走上之路啊
you might end up regretting it.
你有可能反而会后悔
Life is just like that.
就是人生就是如此
So, for me personally,
所以我们就是说呃对于我来讲的话
I need to be free.
我需要将来自由啊
This is very important.
这是一个很重要的
Without freedom,
你没有自由
many things lack a foundation.
很多东西就没有一个前提
Wealth brings freedom
财富有财富的自由
Action
行动
brings freedom too
有行动的自由啊
You only have the freedom to move
你只有迁徙有自由
Action is what grants freedom
行动才有自由
Only action brings freedom
只有行动有自由
Our endeavors can only thrive with freedom So no one should force me to stay in one place Or because of a mortgage That would be even more absurd. Or because of the house. Because of the car, it’s just absurd, you know.
我们的事业才有自由 所以不能因为任何人而把我强行留在一个地方 或者因为房贷 那就更扯淡了 或者因为房子 因为车就这种扯淡了哈
The child has no choice.
孩子没有办法
The child can’t bear to part with it.
孩子没有办法割舍
Parents are born with it, right?
父母也是是天生的
Isn’t that right?
对不对
This is a forced connection.
这是一种强扭带
So, in this case, it can’t be as strong.
所以这个东西来讲就没有办法那么强力的啊
At the very least, I don’t want such reasons to hold me back
起码我不要因为这样的原因束缚我啊
As they say, where there’s a stepmother, there’s a stepfather
所谓的有后妈就会有后爸啊
Exactly
就是这样
Now that you have Guo Fenyang
你有了郭汾阳
Your care for Guo Qilin naturally diminishes
你自然对郭麒麟的关爱就少了
That’s right
就是这样
So, from the perspective of protecting a child
所以对于我一个孩子保护的角度来讲的话
I wouldn’t choose to remarry
我也不会选择再婚啊
I even think that the benefits others could bring me are minimal
甚至我认为别人能给我带来的收益是小的
And the burden others bring to me is significant.
而别人给我带来的负担是大的啊
Many people do not contribute to my career.
很多人对我的事业并没有帮助啊
He just depletes my resources.
他只是在消耗我的财富啊
And sex is just a fleeting moment.
而性就是那一瞬间的事情啊
From a long-term perspective on life,
从长远的人生的角度来看
Many people don't even catch my attention.
很多人对我来讲是没有注意的
He can't help me achieve any of my dreams.
他不能帮我完成任何的梦想
He can't help me fill the gaps in my family either. And I still have to allocate some of my time and energy. Money can't always be there to accompany someone. So, when we talk about it, We say that we are all wanderers in this world,
他也不能帮我去完成我家庭现在所在的缺失 而我还要分出一部分时间精力 金钱里啊去陪伴这个人 所以来讲的话 咱们说呃同是天涯沦落
Strangers meeting, why should we have met before?
人相逢何必曾相识
At every stage of life,
就是每一个阶段时候
What you want is different.
你要的东西是不一样的啊
But I always find that, whether I was in my teens,
但是我始终发现就是无论是我十几岁啊
In my twenties,
20几岁
Or in my thirties,
30几岁
In my forties
40几岁时候
I pursued the same thing
我追求的同样的是一件东西
freedom
就是自由
freedom is crucial
自由很重要啊
freedom doesn't mean I have to go somewhere
自由不代表说我非得去哪儿啊
sometimes staying in
有的时候不出门
not replying to messages
不回信息
is also a form of freedom
也是一种自由
I really hate replying to others' messages
我很讨厌回别人信息
I really hate calling people at fixed times
很讨厌固定时间给人打电话
It feels like punching a clock for a task
像像做任务一样打卡啊
I also hate when others interfere with how I spend my money
我也很讨厌别人干涉我该怎样花钱
or how I live my life
该怎样生活
or where I choose to live
该去哪儿生活
All these things just hold me back
这些东西都是耽误我的
And the reason a place attracts me
而一个地方之所以吸引我啊
To put it bluntly, it’s because there are beautiful girls
说白了那就是有漂亮的姑娘啊
Young girls
有年轻的姑娘
This place really draws me in.
这个地方就很吸引我
So, for me,
所以对我来讲
I have a low need for pairing up with others,
我对跟其他人搭对儿啊
whether it's just companionship or becoming a couple. Most people don't know how to help me, and most people can't really help me either. Marrying a man, for clothes and food, he needs to find someone who can be a financial support.
结伴或者说成为夫妻这一点的这个需求是很低的 大部分人啊并不知道该怎么样帮助我 大部分人也不可能真正去帮助我 嫁汉嫁汉 穿衣吃饭 他需要找到的是一个钱包啊
An ATM that lets you spend money
能够花钱的ATM啊
Of course, this has a bit of a derogatory tone
当然来讲这个有点贬低对方的意思了
But in reality
但是实际上来讲
When you start a family
你要组建家庭
It does require a significant amount of material resources
就是要消耗大量物质财富
That's just how it is
就是这样
Right?
对不对
So for me
所以对于我来讲
In this aspect
对这方面啊
The desire for the opposite sex is gradually decreasing.
对异性的这个需求啊越来越降低了
So, over time, the importance of love itself isn't as highly regarded.
所以慢慢的对对爱情本身呢也不是那么看重
However, this shouldn't negate the role of love in human society.
但是不能因为这样就否定了爱情对人类社会的作用啊
If one can find a suitable partner,
人如果能找到一个如意郎君
finding a soulmate is indeed a wonderful thing.
能找到一个倾心的伴侣还是件很好的事
There are many aspects of life,
因为人生有很多事情啊
which one doesn't want to face alone.
他不想独自面对
For instance, hunger,
比如饥饿啊
illness, and death.
这个疾病死亡啊
It's good to spend some money on your partner.
给对方花点钱啊
Sharing your life with them is a wonderful thing.
跟对方共享你的人生是很好的事情
But for me,
但是对于我来讲的话
it's still the same principle, as someone on a spiritual path, there are many lessons to learn in this life, many tasks to accomplish. Practicing in the secular world has its own set of challenges. But speaking for myself,
还是那句话 作为一个修行之人来讲的话 这一生要完成的课题啊 要完成的任务还很多啊 修俗世更有更有它的挑战意义 但是作为我来讲的话
The most crucial thing is the freedom to migrate.
最重要的就是一个迁徙自由啊
If you get married, you can't achieve this.
如果找了老婆就做不到这一点啊
No matter who you marry,
无论你找的是谁
they will have parents,
他总有父母吧
and things they are emotionally attached to,
他总有自己的这牵肠挂肚的东西吧
they will have a career,
他也有了事业
a source of their livelihood,
他都有事业的来源吧
a place to live,
他在哪生活
a home to stay in.
在哪住
These are all issues.
这都是问题啊
So once you get a wife,
所以一旦找了老婆
once you have a steady girlfriend,
一旦找了固定的女朋友
there will be a lot of troubles waiting for you.
就会有很多的麻烦等待着你
So for me,
所以对于我来讲
being single doesn't mean I can be with someone today
一个独身主义不是代表着说我今天能跟他
and with someone else tomorrow without any moral burden.
明天能跟他没有道德负担
That's not what it means.
不是这个意思
It means that being single is about maintaining an independent life state.
而是说一个独身主义相对于一个独立的一种人生状态啊
It's not that there's absolutely no girlfriend at all
并不是说完完全全就没有女朋友啊
But relatively speaking
但是相对来讲的话
We don't get entangled with each other
互相不牵扯
We don't interfere with each other's lifestyle
互相不去干扰对方的生活形态
This is really important
这个东西很重要啊
It's a high-level form of companionship
这是一种高层次高层次的高阶段的一种陪伴
I also think that in the context of future solo living Many people should truly have this kind of relationship Don't let anyone change your current lifestyle Don't let anyone alter their life path for you
我也觉得是未来独身主义来讲的话 很多人真正应该有的那种状态 你不要因为任何人改变现在目前的生活方式 也不要让任何人为你去改变他的生活轨迹
It's just not worth it
这都是不值得的
So I think with urbanization
所以我觉得随着城市化啊
And with the advancement of technology
随着科技的进步
People gradually breaking free from the constraints of traditional family values
人慢慢的脱离以前的家庭的观念的束缚呢
Is very necessary
是很有必要的
As for how humans will survive and reproduce in the future
至于那个时候人类怎么生存繁衍啊
I actually feel that my current state is really great
我倒觉得我倒觉得我现在这个状态非常的好啊
I do have descendants
就是也有后代啊
Life is also about freedom.
生活也自由
Of course, you know,
当然来讲的话
you can never completely break away from your parents,
你永远不可能完全脱离父母
right?
对不对
but I think some people have distant family ties,
但是我认为呢有些人六亲缘浅
don’t have a good relationship with their parents,
跟父母的关系不好啊
and that can actually be a good thing.
反而是件好事
They don’t have kids,
也没孩子
and they don’t have many worries.
也没牵挂
I consider myself invincible.
自己是无敌之人
So I think this is a truly perfect state.
所以我觉得这样是一种啊非常完美的状态
But no matter what,
但是无论怎么样
I just want to tell everyone,
我就跟大家说
If you love romance,
如果你是喜欢爱情
pursue love,
追求爱情
attain love,
得到了爱情
or don't get love,
没得到爱情啊
or you feel being single is better.
还是你觉得独身好啊
Being single, you've found someone who likes you
独身你找到了有喜欢你的人
or you're completely and utterly independent All four of these states are perfectly fine as long as you feel at peace with yourself Peace of mind is where heaven lies Often, this is how things are If you're not at ease and always longing for a different state, you might just be missing out
还是完完全全是一个独立的一个人 这个时候这四种状态都是可以的 你只要自己觉得心安就可以啊 心安之处啊便是天堂 很多的时候就是这样 如果你心不安总是在一种状态想另一种状态你就未尝不可惜啊
So, often, it's through experiencing marriage that
所以很多的时候就是你要经历过婚姻
you truly discover who you are
你才知道自己到底是什么样的人啊
You know, every time I go through a marriage, or rather,
你像我每一次经历婚姻经历这个啊
it's not that every time I go through a marriage,
当然不是说每一次经历婚姻
but when I experience a long-term relationship,
经历一种这种长时间的这种这种关系的时候
I get really frustrated.
我都是很烦恼啊
I don't want to fully dedicate my experiences to another person.
我不愿意把自己的经历完完全全啊奉献给另外一个人啊
And I feel that in reality,
而且我觉得在现实当中
no one can truly keep up with my mental and intellectual level.
没有人真正能够追得上我的精神水平跟这个思想水平啊
Many people are not on the same level as me.
很多的人跟我并不对等啊
This isn't a boastful statement
这不是一种骄傲的话
but rather that everyone's path is unique
而是一种每个人追寻的路径是不一样的
He doesn't know what I'm thinking
他并不知道我现在在想什么
What's troubling me
苦恼什么啊
or what worries I might have
也不知道为我问我何忧
It's this kind of thing
就是这种东西
You don't know if the other person is on the same wavelength as you And some trivial matters, how to put it I'm not particularly interested in the daily necessities like firewood, rice, oil, salt, soy sauce, vinegar, and tea It's not that I have a strong pursuit of spiritual life
就是你不知道对方在精神上是否与你契合 而一些鸡毛蒜皮的怎么说呢 那个柴米油盐酱醋茶这种东西我也不是特别的感兴趣 我也不是因为我对精神生活的追求是很强的啊
I have a weaker desire for material life
我对物质生活的追求是比较弱的
You all can see that my material desires are pretty low
你大家也看我的物欲就是比较差啊
Drive a small car
开个小车
Live in a modest little house
住个小破房啊
That's all I need
就完了啊
I don't have many material desires
没有什么太大的物质上的欲望
Of course, I've thought about living a better life
当然我也想过很好的生活
But after weighing the options, I feel that a better life means more wealth
但权衡之后总觉得所谓的更好的生活意味着更多的财富啊
It means higher maintenance costs
意味着更大的维持费
The expenses for maintenance
维持的开销
To me
对我来讲的话
To achieve such a lifestyle
为了获得那样的生活啊
The price to pay might be even higher
所付出的代价可能更高啊
When it comes to love
所以爱情这个东西来讲的话
If freedom is what you seek
就是若为自由
Both can be sacrificed
故两者皆可抛啊
Often, that's how it is
很多的时候就是这样啊
Of course, everyone has a different order of priorities in life.
当然每个人啊他人生当中的排序不一样
Some people place themselves first.
有人会把自己放在第一位
Others put their family and children at the top.
有人会把家庭把孩子放在第一位
I also prioritize my children.
当然我也是把孩子放在第一位的
However, speaking more broadly,
但是更多的来讲的话
the highest priority should be oneself.
优先级更高的肯定是自己啊
Because only when one exists, can one pursue certain things. So, love, as a form of social guidance, He’s definitely inclined to help you find a partner.
因为只有自己这个存在的话 自己才能去追求一些东西啊 所以爱情这个东西本身作为社会化的规劝呢 他肯定是倾向于让你找到伴侣的
He wants you to have children, after all.
让你生下孩子了啊
As a society,
这个是作为一个社会
it’s bound to promote this idea.
他肯定要这么去宣传
It’s going to say this,
这么去说
because it needs to supply the society with fresh labor.
因为要为这个社会提供新鲜的劳动力
Since you, as a labor force,
因为你作为一个劳动力
are getting old,
你已经老了
right?
对不对
You should provide society with a new workforce.
你要为这社会啊再提供一个新的劳动力
For you,
那对于你来说
it means completing the generational upgrade.
他就完成了更新换代
Before you completely pass away,
在你完全死去之前啊
you should spend your money on this.
你把这个东西把你的钱花出去
This is the greatest contribution to society.
这就是对社会最大的贡献
But you should understand, as a person,
但是你要知道作为一个人来讲的话
you wouldn't think that way, right?
你肯定不是这样去想的对吧
As an individual
你作为一个个体的人
You can't just think about what society expects from you
你不能光去想这个社会对你的期待是什么
or what your family expects
还有家庭的期待
or what your partner expects
还有另一半对你的期待
or what your children expect
还有孩子对你的期待
or what you expect from yourself
还有你自己对自己的期待到底是什么
This is the time for you to figure it out
这个时候你就要自己琢磨好啊
Don't expect me to give you the answer
不要让我告诉你答案
You need to go out and find it
要去自己去追寻
It's that simple
就这么简单的一个事情
So, whether you get love or not, there's no need to be sad.
所以爱情这东西得到得不到都不要难过啊
If you get it, you'll have the worries that come with it. If you don't, you'll have a different set of worries. But no matter what, the place you are in at this moment is where you find peace. No matter what, your current state is already a perfect state.
得到了有得到的烦恼 得不到有得不到的烦恼啊 但是无论怎么样啊 此时正在之处便是心安之处啊 就是无论怎么样 你现在这个状态就已经是一个完美的一个状态
Don't feel ashamed
不要因为单身
just because you're single.
你就会觉得很羞愧
Don't think that just because you have a wife now
也不要觉得你现在有了老婆了
you're in the safe zone
你就进了保险箱去了
endless troubles are still waiting for you
无尽的烦恼还在等待着你啊
so no matter how you look at it
所以无论怎么样来讲的话
it's a classic case of the grass being greener on the other side
这就是一个围城啊
but our aging
但是咱们的衰老
our birth, aging, sickness, and death are certain
咱们的生老病死是一定的
they are inevitable
是注定的啊
death is a given
这个死亡是一种约定
Good cultivation
好的修行
It's just like that
本身就是这样
But don't be sad because of this
但不要因为这个而就难过
But while we are alive
但是在我们活的时候
We need to create the value we want
要创造我们自己想要的价值
This is crucial
这是很关键
So for me
所以对我来讲的话
No one can truly accompany me on my journey in the future
谁将来也不可能真正能陪我浪迹天涯
No one can always be there for me
谁也不可能君去陪着我
To explore everything I want to explore
去探索一切我想探索的东西
Even my parents can't be with me all the time
甚至我的父母都不可能陪着我啊
My child has their own path in life
我的孩子他有自己的人生之路
So for me
所以对于我来讲的话
In the end, the only one who will be with me is myself
最终陪伴我的只有我自己啊
Ultimately, the person you truly love is a reflection of yourself
最终你真正爱的人其实也是你自己的一个投射
Tsk
啧
He isn't a real person This person changes with time As your appearance changes, as you age, it will keep evolving. Someone you like in your twenties, you might not have liked in your teens.
他不是一个实际存在的人 这个人随着岁月 随着你的相貌 随着你的年龄 他会不停的改变 20多岁喜欢的人 可能你十几岁的时候就不会喜欢啊
Someone you like in your thirties,
30多岁喜欢的人
you might not like anymore in your forties.
你可能40多岁就不再喜欢了
That's just how it is.
就是这样啊
So people always change with these things.
所以人永远是随着这个东西在变
It's always about projecting your own desires
永远是把把自己的某种愿望
some ideals onto others
某种理想投射到别人身上而已
until the person can perfectly meet your needs
等到这个人能够完美满足你的时候呢
you'll feel that this person is great
你会觉得这个人很好
but when the person can't meet your needs as well
等这个人不是很能满足你的时候
you tend to control others
你就倾向于控制别人
or you might let go
或者倾向于放手啊
this dynamic is quite subtle
这个东西就是很微妙
so no matter what
哎所以无论如何
Actually, I mentioned in the last episode
其实我在说上一期的时候就在说
that a person's life is essentially a reality fantasy created by oneself
人一辈子其实都是在一个自己创造的一种现实幻想当中呢
to complete our lives
啊完成我们的这一生啊
Everyone to you is an NPC, this world is a creation of your own heart
所有人对你来讲都是NPC啊啊这个世界是你自己的心
crafted by your own mind
自己的大脑创造出来的
it doesn't truly exist
它并不真实存在
and it's a shared fantasy
而且是一种共识幻想啊
this little universe in which you exist
这个你自己存在这个小宇宙呢
is called an independent fantasy
这叫独立幻想啊
The world itself is a consensus of imagination. So you can't prove that the blue someone else sees isn't the red you see. You can never fully prove that the world others see is the same world you see.
这个世界本身是一种共识幻想 所以你无法证明别人眼里的蓝色 不是你眼中的红色 你永远没有办法完完全全证明别人看到的世界 跟你看到的世界是一个世界
This is at the heart of our philosophical thinking.
这也就是咱们哲学思想的一个核心所在
So you don't need to overly concern yourself with others' opinions and thoughts.
所以你也不用完完全全去在意别人的看法跟别人的想法
You should live more authentically.
你应该活的更加自我一些
You should be a bit more self-loving.
应该做一个比较自恋的一个人
It's important to focus on your deep feelings about everything.
应该注重自我在每件事情上的深知啊的感受
All of these.
所有的这些
What are your thoughts?
那你的感想
What have you experienced?
你的体会
These are part of the experiences you gather.
这些东西是你收集的经验的一部分
These are valuable things on your life's journey.
这个东西是你人生路上宝贵的东西
These are the most precious things.
这个东西是最宝贵的东西
So, love itself,
所以爱情这个东西本身
Actually, the reason you pursue external things is
其实你之所以会去追求一些外在的东西
It's due to a lack of something within you.
正是因为你内在的一些东西的缺乏
You pursue what you yearn for.
你渴望什么就会去追求什么
You hope your partner brings what you desire.
你渴望什么就希望对方带什么
This is a very normal thing.
这是一种很正常的东西
Of course, you have primal instincts.
当然来讲你有原始本能
There are aspects related to sexuality.
有性的这部分的东西
You have certain ideals about love.
你有一些对于爱情
Idealized parts of these things.
对于这些东西的理想化的一些部分
But no matter what, You will eventually be defeated by reality. You will have to consider practical matters eventually. Whether to move to his city, Or have him move for you,
但是无论怎么样 你最终啊会被现实所击败 你最终会要一些现实的考量啊 到底是搬到他的城市去 还是让他为你而搬家啊
Who should live closer to their parents,
你到底是应该在离的谁的父母更近一些
What the child’s last name should be,
孩子应该姓什么
Where you should buy a house,
你们应该买哪里的房子
A car you don’t like, but he does.
一个车子你不喜欢他却喜欢
Should you buy it or not?
你到底要不要买
So there’s an endless array of choices that can be exhausting.
所以是无尽的这种选择上的困扰
I find it incredibly tiring.
让我觉得非常的疲惫啊
My life should be dedicated to greater pursuits,
我的人生应该去用作一些更伟大的工作当中
Not wasted on trivial matters.
而不是在这些鸡毛蒜皮的小事上浪费时间啊
So, to me, marriage is an experience to go through.
所以来讲的话婚姻对我来讲就是一个体验的一个过程
I’ve experienced it already.
我已经体验过了
I know what it’s all about.
也知道是怎么回事了
So, in that sense,
所以来讲的话
Life is more about exploration.
人生更多的东西呢是在探索当中
There are greater challenges in life.
人生也有更伟大的课题啊
Don’t let love tie you down.
不要因为爱情而绊住手脚
But at the same time, I say,
但是我同时说
Love is great.
爱情是很伟大的
Love can transcend social classes,
爱情这个东西能够跨越阶级啊
Even races,
跨越甚至跨越种族
And time itself.
跨越时间
It’s truly great.
他是很伟大的
It’s a reason for people to keep living.
是人活下去的一个理由
Of course, there’s romantic love,
当然来讲有男女之情
And the love between mother and child,
有母子之情啊
And love for one’s country. These are all different things. But no matter what, Love is a great thing. Love itself is a great reason why humanity has come this far.
有这个对祖国的爱 这个东西都是不一样的 但是无论怎么样 爱情是一种伟大的东西 爱本身是一个人类之所以能够走到今天的一个很伟大的事情
Your compassion for others,
你对别人的同情心
Is also a part of love.
这也是爱的一部分啊
For example, the suffering of children in Gaza today,
比如说你像加沙的儿童今天所遭受的苦难
You can empathize with others as you would with your own family,
你能够老吾老以及人之老
And care for others’ children as you would your own.
幼吾幼以及人之幼
This is indeed a manifestation of your inherent kindness.
这确实是你的一个人的善良本性啊
The role it plays.
做做所采取的作用
So, often times,
所以很多的时候来讲
We say love and hate are two sides of the same coin.
我们说爱跟恨是一部分啊
You have love because,
你之所以有爱
You also have hate.
所以你才会有恨啊
Right?
你之所以对吧
You deeply love your fellow countrymen,
你特别深爱你的同胞
So you hate invaders.
所以你就憎恨侵略者这个东西
That’s how it is.
就是这样
You love peace for humanity,
你之所以你爱人类的和平
So you hate those who start wars.
你就憎恨那些发动战争的人啊
But everything has its roots and branches,
但是凡是万物都有怎么说呢
Complex interrelationships.
盘根错节的这个因缘关系啊
So, let’s not get bogged down in these details today.
所以呢咱们不要今天去揪这个理
But no matter what,
但无论怎么样来讲
I want to bless everyone,
我就想祝福大家
Whether you choose a life of solitude,
就是无论你走上的是独身之路
Or encounter multiple partners in life,
还是你在人生当中会遇到数个伴侣
Or stay with someone for the long haul, don’t hesitate, Live without regret, Be proud of yourself, Be proud of the choices you make, Bless others in their choices, Of course, see others’ pain,
还是你人生中你会跟跟别人长相厮守都不要啊 应该恕己无愧 应该以自己为荣啊 应该以自己选择的方式为荣 应该去祝福别人的选择啊 当然来讲也看到别人的痛苦
But make your own choices,
自己呢拥有自己的选择呢
And be responsible for those choices,
我就为这种选择买单啊
Bear the consequences of your choices,
我就为这种选择承担最后的后果
And it doesn’t matter,
然后呢无所谓啊
No matter what,
无论怎么样
A life pursuing what you seek, whether you achieve it or not, is a complete life.
都是这么一生追求得到追求不到都是完整的一生
Don’t feel ashamed because of it.
不要因为这个而感到惭愧